Guide to the Thomas Heazle Parke Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Thomas Heazle Parke papers
1881-1914
MS 1643
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.25
The papers consist of letters written by Thomas H. Parke to his sister, Isabel Beatty, about his travels with Henry M. Stanley in Africa. Also included are telegrams and newspapers clippings.
Parke, Thomas Heazle, 1857-1893
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Charles Apfelbaum, 1993.
Existence and Location of Copies
Entire collection is also available on microfilm (163 frames on 1 reel, 35mm.) from Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library, at cost. Order no. HM263.
Biographical / Historical
Thomas Heazle Parke was born in Ireland on November 27, 1857 and entered the British Army Medical Service in 1881 as a surgeon. He saw service in Egypt between 1882 and 1885, and accompanied Henry M. Stanley's expedition in 1887 as an unpaid volunteer. Throughout the expedition Parke commanded a company in addition to acting as the medical and sanitation officer. He returned to England in 1890 and was attached to the 2nd Lifeguards in London, and was subsequently employed at the Royal Victoria Hospital, Netley. Parke died suddenly on September 10, 1893. He was the author of articles on his travels and on professional subjects.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of letters written by Thomas H. Parke to his sister, Isabel Beatty, about his travels with Henry M. Stanley in Africa. Also included are telegrams and newspapers clippings.
Conditions Governing Access
The entire collection is available on microfilm. Patrons must use FILM HM 263 instead of the originals.
Explorers -- Africa, Sub-Saharan; Explorers -- Great Britain; Africa; Parke, Thomas Heazle, 1857-1893; Stanley, Henry M. (Henry Morton), 1841-1904
- Inventory
  Scope and Contents
  The Thomas H. Parke Papers consist primarily of letters from Thomas Heazle Parke to his sister, Isabel Beatty, regarding his travels with Henry M. Stanley.
  Correspondence to and from others and printed material complete the collection which was purchased in 1993.
  - Annotated envelopes, 1885-1893, undated (Box 1, Folder 1, Reel 1U)
  - Chinese writing, undated (Box 1, Folder 2, Reel 1U)
  - Correspondence from T.H.P. to Isabel Beatty, 1881-1893, undated (Box 1, Folder 3, Reel 1U)
  - Correspondence from T.H.P. to others, 1882, 1885 (Box 1, Folder 4, Reel 1U)
  - Correspondence of others, 1889, 1890, undated (Box 1, Folder 5, Reel 1U)
  - Photograph, undated (Box 1, Folder 6, Reel 1U)
  - Printed material, 1883, 1911, 1914, undated (Box 1, Folder 7, Reel 1U)
  - Transcription of correspondence, 1885, 1890, undated (Box 1, Folder 8, Reel 1U)
  - Unidentified correspondence, undated (Box 1, Folder 9, Reel 1U)